On today's video, we are going to make
pistachio honey gelato. It's delicious
and it's surprisingly easy to
[Music]
make. Yeah, pistachio is actually one of
my mom's favorite ice cream flavors. And
I It's been quite a while since I made
it to be fair. Um, back when we were in
the UK is when I made it last. It's not
as difficult as people make out and
we're going to go through it today.
We're going to reduce as it's gelato,
it's higher sugar. So, if you don't
know, there's a whole video that I'll
put a link in. I'll probably put up here
and down in the description that
describes the differences between
American ice cream and gelato, which is
traditionally Italian. In the short,
gelato is lower fat than American ice
cream, but much higher sugar. Um, and
also has less overrun. So though the
overrun we can't really control in some
home ice cream machines even less in a
ninja creamy but we can still do things
because by the inclusion of a stabilizer
like guar gum or zantham gum we can
increase overrun a little bit in the
lower cost machines which is perfect for
the home user. So without further ado
let's see what we need for this
delicious honey pistachio gelato.
You are going to need 226 gram of cream,
around 33 to 35% fat, 1,28 g of milk,
either 2% or 3.25%, so that's semi-kmed
or full fat milk, 205 g of sugar, 154 g
of honey, 50 g of skim milk powder.
Optionally, 4 g of almond extract.
You're also going to need 150 g of
roasted salted pistachios, 50 g of
finely chopped chocolate between 60 and
70%. And then your optional stabilizer.
Now, it sounds like a lot going in and
there's some things that you don't have
to put in there. The chocolate itself,
that's a shave chocolate. So, that's a
personal preference. Having some shaved
chocolate throughout this makes it just
incredibly good. So, I do recommend
that. Stabilizer is always optional as I
say, but it does make your ice cream
really, really good, much better, and it
gives it decent longevity in the freezer
as well. Plus, it reduces the ice
crystal formation, so your ice cream is
delicious whenever you want to eat it.
So, without further ado, what we need to
do is get our liquids measured into a
pan and just get them warming up. So,
let's do that.
I'm going to use a stabilizer. So, I'm
going to take
my 5 g of
sugar. I'm going to
use part of my 442
blend. There we go. 4 g. It's in a
special ingredient sub, but it's not
what's in there. um recommend you go and
watch uh one of my videos on ice cream
stabilizers if you're interested in
getting into that kind of thing. Really
does make ice cream even ninja creamy
recipes much much better. So there's
that. We have our honey and our skim
milk powder.
So it's kind of optional the skim milk
powder in this recipe. It's bit low in
milk solids without it. And it really
does create that perfect texture by by
adding it. The point of skimm milk
powder is to increase milk solids. So
milk
proteins without adding any more liquid.
Um you can do that in a commercial
environment by reducing part during the
pasteurization phase and it will reduce
the amount of liquid which will then
subsequently increase the amount of milk
solids and protein. You can kind of do
that at home by um as you warm up your
mixture on a hob, you will cause
evaporation of the liquids or the water
specifically and that will increase your
milk solids, but it's quite difficult to
gauge that. That's why we use it. That's
why it's super important. Stir that
together. Honey, I'm using this. This is
a local honey. Old Grumps honey is
perfectly named for me. Um, this is this
is
unpasteurized, but use what's right for
you. We're going to put this on the hob
and just get it warming up. This
stabilizer will need ATC 185F. So, let's
get it up to that point and then we'll
take it off the heat and bring it back
here. Whilst we do that, we're going to
deal with our pistachios.
So,
pistachios, if you have a Costco around
you, that's the cheapest place to buy
them by a long shot, by a Kentucky mile.
Roasted salted
pistachios. I mean, they're
delicious. One of the big crossover
flavors is the use of almond extract in
pistachio ice cream. And that is
historically done because they share a
lot of flavonoids and
flavoronoids, which means that when you
make pistachio ice cream, you can boost
that pistachio flavor by the addition of
almond extract. You don't want to go too
far with the almond extract cuz then
you're just making almond ice cream with
some nuts in it. Um, and that is an
optional ingredient here. You can,
because this is a large batch, you can
add four grams of almond extract. You
also don't have to add that much. You
can add just a touch because this is a
pistachio honey gelato. So, it's a
combination flavor. But what we're going
to do is we're going to start with 150 g
of our pistachios. Make sure you don't
allow your honey to burn on the bottom
of your pan. Keep it
moving. 150 g pistachios. What we're
going to do is we're going to put these
in a little mini
blender
and we're going to blend these for quite
a while in this blender anyway. It's
it's this is only a little baby one.
You're not going to be able to turn this
into paste in in this without the
addition of a liquid. And that's what
we're going to do after our base is
ready.
You've seen what the pistachio paste now
looks like. It goes quite
hard. Um, just to recap, like this. And
that's because there's not a lot of
liquid in here. And this blender isn't
powerful enough to turn this into like a
butter, like a peanut butter, pistachio
butter. So, what we need to do is just
add a bit of liquid. Now, historically,
you will see people online saying, "Oh,
you shouldn't add liquid to any kind of
nut butter because you'll make it split
or you'll make it seize." Well, that's
not really the case because it actually
what you need to do is just add more.
So, we're going to start
off by just
adding a couple of spoonfuls of our hot
milk and get it blending again.
There we go. Quick check on the
sides. Check down the bottom.
Beautiful. And what you're left
with is this
glorious pistachio
paste that is absolutely perfect for our
gelato. So, let's get all of that into
here. Just going to stir that together.
Right, with that stirred together, we're
not going to add any artificial
colorings. This is a natural pistachio
color. You can add green food coloring
if you want to to really bring that
green right out, but I don't think we
need
to. So, we're going to chill this in the
fridge. There's a lot of nut solids in
here, so you're going to get some
floating to the top. You might even get
some dropping to the bottom. Don't
stress about it. That's what it's going
to do. So, if you want to chill this
down in a nice bath, then do that. I'm
just going to put this in the
refrigerator cuz I want those flavors of
that honey and those pistachios to boost
with a nice rest of about 4 to 5 hours.
Then, we will come back and do what we
need to do. So, after it's chilled in
the fridge, again, this is like four or
five hours, let those flavors develop.
Get in there with a whisk and give it a
good stir. Get all those solids mixed
back in and get it loaded into your
machine to churn. My machine's been
pre-chilled for about 10 minutes and
we're going to do a Ninja Creamy one as
well. So, that's a Ninja Creamy Deluxe
tub. Whilst everything is churning,
we're going to get our chocolate. This
is Calibbo um 80% chocolate. Right at
the end of the churn, you're going to
get that put in there. It's aching to
kind of like Hand's Belgian chocolate
size chunks of chocolate. My mouth is
watering just talking about it. Time to
dish up and load up our tubs. This is a
large batch as I said before, so feel
free to just knock it in half or do
whatever you need to do. But once that's
ready, it's in the freezer for a
good 12 hours just to get that hardened
off. We're going to take it out and
scoop some up. Let's point it up at the
camera. Let's have a look. Yep, that
looks incredible. Get some dished up.
And here we go. Less talk, more honey
pistachio
gelato. Perfect
pistachio honey gelato with chocolate
chips. I mean, they're not chocolate
chips. They're kind of chocolate
flexcks. The texture of this is aken to
Hagen's Belgian chocolate.
So, scoops
perfectly. I probably actually just
reduced the sugar or the honey ever so
slightly cuz for most people, I think
this is going to be a little bit too
soft. But, as you can see, it's straight
out of the freezer. There's no weird
editing. Straight out of the freezer,
the scoops perfectly, which means some
people might prefer it a little bit
harder. In which case, remove like 20 g
worth of honey. that would absolutely do
the trick for this. Honey is essentially
a natural version of corn syrup, which
is a balance of fructose and
glucose. It it does the same thing as
corn syrup. Corn syrup is man-made and
honey is not. The taste of the
pistachios is perfect. That undertone of
the honey comes through. Obviously,
depending on what honey you use, some
honeys are really strong flavored. So,
just use one that you like. I used to
back in the UK used to get my honey from
Quint Honey Farm.
down in the southwest. And that had a
glorious flavor, lovely color, one of
the best honeys I've ever had in my
entire life. I now get old Grumps honey
because it's local. Uh it doesn't have a
huge amount of flavor. And that's the
same for all honey where I live just
because of what grows naturally here.
Basically, we live in a desert which is
covered in snow for 5 months and then is
bone dry for the rest of the year. So
this time it's the Ninja Creamy's turn.
And as you can see, lovely smooth top
there. Whilst that's in the machine
spinning on ice cream setting, we are
going to get some of our chocolate. This
is Belalade chocolate. I think it's 80%
cacao as well. So once the first spin's
done, we're going to make that big divot
in the middle, put our chocolate in, and
we're going to pop it back on to the
add-in setting. It doesn't decimate in
the Creamy Deluxe like it does in the
other ones. Let's get some of this
dished up into my little tub. Look at
that. The ninja creamy one. I mean, you
know, even though it doesn't have any
overrun, it's still
delicious. This is
delicious. Pistachio honey gelato. Those
chocolate flexcks are out. Perfect. You
get some that are just big enough to
bite, so you get a lovely taste of that
as well. This is right up there. As I
say, this is in my top 10 ice creams,
and I'm going to make another batch of
this very, very soon. Thanks very much
for watching. Don't forget to like and
subscribe if you want to see lots more
gelato and American ice cream recipes. I
talk about the science of ice cream in
my videos. I don't just make crap and
hope for the best like a lot of people
out there. So, if you want to learn how
to make the best gelato and ice cream
possible, make sure to like and
subscribe. See you next week. Heat. Hey,
Heat.
[Music]